<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Gnoll</name>
		<update version="0.2">
			<file name="gnoll.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/MylesWritesCode/homebrew-dnd/master/homebrew/races/gnoll.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>
	<element name="Gnoll" type="Race" source="Homebrew" id="ID_RACE_GNOLL">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">Whether united under the leadership of a mighty warlock or having fought to a standstill after years of conflict, gnoll and human tribes sometimes form alliances, joining forces into a larger horde to the terror of civilized lands nearby. When these alliances are sealed by marriages, gnolls are born. Some gnolls rise to become proud chiefs of gnoll tribes, their human blood giving them an edge over their full-blooded gnoll rivals. Some venture into the world to prove their worth among humans and other more civilized races. Many of these become adventurers, achieving greatness for their mighty deeds and notoriety for their barbaric customs and savage fury.</p>
			<h4>SCARRED AND STRONG</h4>
			<p>Half-orcs’ grayish pigmentation, sloping foreheads, jutting jaws, prominent teeth, and towering builds make their gnollish heritage plain for all to see. Gnolls stand between 6 and 7 feet tall and usually weigh between 180 and 250 pounds.</p>
			<p class="indent">Orcs regard battle scars as tokens of pride and ornamental scars as things of beauty. Other scars, though, mark an gnoll or gnoll as a former slave or a disgraced exile. Any gnoll who has lived among or near gnolls has scars, whether they are marks of humiliation or of pride, recounting their past exploits and injuries. Such a gnoll living among humans might display these scars proudly or hide them in shame.</p>
			<h4>THE MARK OF GRUUMSH</h4>
			<p>The one-eyed god Gruumsh created the gnoll s, and even those gnolls who turn away from his worship can’t fully escape his influence. The same is true of gnolls, though their human blood moderates the impact of their orcish heritage. Some gnolls hear the whispers of Gruumsh in their dreams, calling them to unleash the rage that simmers within them. Others feel Gruumsh’s exultation when they join in melee combat—and either exult along with him or shiver with fear and loathing. Gnolls are not evil by nature, but evil does lurk within them, whether they embrace it or rebel against it.</p>
			<p class="indent">Beyond the rage of Gruumsh, gnolls feel emotion powerfully. Rage doesn’t just quicken their pulse, it makes their bodies burn. An insult stings like acid, and sadness saps their strength. But they laugh loudly and heartily, and simple bodily pleasures—feasting, drinking, wrestling, drumming, and wild dancing—fill their hearts with joy. They tend to be short-tempered and sometimes sullen, more inclined to action than contemplation and to fighting than arguing. The most accomplished gnolls are those with enough selfcontrol to get by in a civilized land.</p>
			<h4>TRIBES AND SLUMS</h4>
			<p>Gnolls most often live among gnoll s. Of the other races, humans are most likely to accept gnolls, and halforcs almost always live in human lands when not living among gnoll tribes. Whether proving themselves among rough barbarian tribes or scrabbling to survive in the slums of larger cities, gnolls get by on their physical might, their endurance, and the sheer determination they inherit from their human ancestry.</p>
			<h4>GNOLL NAMES</h4>
			<p>Gnolls usually have names appropriate to the culture in which they were raised. A gnoll who wants to fit in among humans might trade an gnoll name for a human name. Some gnolls with human names decide to adopt a guttural gnoll name because they think it makes them more intimidating.</p>
			<ul class="unstyled">
				<li><strong>Male Gnoll Names:</strong> Dench, Feng, Gell, Henk, Holg, Imsh, Keth, Krusk, Mhurren, Ront, Shump, Thokk</li>
				<li><strong>Female Gnoll Names:</strong> Baggi, Emen, Engong, Kansif, Myev, Neega, Ovak, Ownka, Shautha, Sutha, Vola, Volen, Yevelda</li>
			</ul>
			<h4>GNOLL TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Your gnoll character has certain traits deriving from your gnoll ancestry.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Dexterity score increases by 1, your Wisdom score increases by 1, and your Constitution score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Gnolls mature a little faster than humans, reaching adulthood around age 14. They age noticeably faster and rarely live longer than 75 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Alignment.</em></strong> Gnolls inherit a tendency toward chaos from their gnoll parents and are not strongly inclined toward good. Gnolls raised among gnolls and willing to live out their lives among them are usually evil.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Gnolls are somewhat larger and bulkier than humans, and they range from 5 to well over 6 feet tall. Your size is Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your base walking speed is 35 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Darkvision.</em></strong> Thanks to your gnoll blood, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Menacing.</em></strong> You gain proficiency in the Intimidation skill.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Relentless Endurance.</em></strong> When you are reduced to 0 hit points but not killed outright, you can drop to 1 hit point instead. You can’t use this feature again until you finish a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Savage Attacks.</em></strong> When you score a critical hit with a melee weapon attack, you can roll one of the weapon’s damage dice one additional time and add it to the extra damage of the critical hit.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write Common and Gnoll. Gnoll is a harsh, grating language with hard consonants. It has no script of its own but is written in the Dwarvish script.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Dench, Feng, Gell, Henk, Holg, Imsh, Keth, Krusk, Mhurren, Ront, Shump, Thokk</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Baggi, Emen, Engong, Kansif, Myev, Neega, Ovak, Ownka, Shautha, Sutha, Vola, Volen, Yevelda</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}}</set>
			<set name="height" modifier="2d10">4'10"</set>
			<set name="weight" modifier="2d6">140 lb.</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="dexterity" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<stat name="innate speed" value="35" bonus="base"/>
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" requirements="!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FILTH_EATERS_GULLET" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_RIPPING_JAWS" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_RAMPAGE" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GHOSTLY_WHISPERS" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BRED_TO_HUNT" requirements="!ID_WOTC_WGTE_GRANTS_DARKMARKED,!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK"/>
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_MM_LANGUAGE_GNOLL" requirements="!ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_DRAGONMARK" />
			<select type="Race Variant" name="Gnoll Variant" supports="Gnoll Variant" optional="true" />
		</rules>
	</element>	
	<element name="Filth Eater's Gullet" type="Racial Trait" source="Homebrew" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FILTH_EATERS_GULLET">
		<description>
			<p>You gain resistance to poison and disease.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You gain resistance to poison and disease.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<!-- <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_INTIMIDATION" /> -->
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_POISON" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_DISEASE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Ripping Jaws" type="Racial Trait" source="Homebrew" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_RIPPING_JAWS">
		<description>
			<p>You can choose to bite as an attack which causes the attack to inflict 1d4 piercing damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can choose to bite as an attack which causes the attack to inflict 1d4 piercing damage.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Rampage" type="Racial Trait" source="Homebrew" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_RAMPAGE">
		<description>
			<p>When you reduce a creature to 0 hit points on your turn with a melee attack, you can spend a bonus action to move up to half your speed and make a bite attack against an enemy that is within range at the end of this move.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When you reduce a creature to 0 hit points on your turn with a melee attack, you can spend a bonus action to move up to half your speed and make a bite attack against an enemy that is within range at the end of this move.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Ghostly Whispers" type="Racial Trait" source="Homebrew" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GHOSTLY_WHISPERS">
		<description>
			<p>You can imitate the voice of any creature you have heard speaking, so long as you speak the same language as that creature.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can imitate the voice of any creature you have heard speaking, so long as you speak the same language as that creature.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Bred to Hunt" type="Racial Trait" source="Homebrew" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BRED_TO_HUNT">
		<description>
			<p>You have Proficiency in Perception and Survival.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have Proficiency in Perception and Survival.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_SURVIVAL" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_PERCEPTION" />
		</rules>
	</element>
</elements>